[Music]
a major disaster is occurring in new
york city this morning
[Applause]
the people who knocked these buildings
down we'll hear all of us soon
[Applause]
after a firefight they killed osama bin
laden and took custody of his body
the world changed on september 11 2001
after the attacks on the united states
and now 20 years on we look back at what
happened how the u.s responded and the
legacy of its so-called war on terror
[Music]
hello welcome to this special edition of
inside america with mirida fahri live in
washington
now we all remember where we were on
that fateful day september 11 2001
a day that would alter the course of
history
wherever you were the movie-like scenes
of planes crashing into the world trade
center the collapse of the twin towers
have left an indelible mark on those of
us who lived it in real time and those
too young to remember or those who were
not even born
and these memories remain vivid to this
day
now on 9 11 i was a new york based
reporter for another international news
network
like millions of people who lived and
worked in manhattan
i started my day with the unimaginable
unfathomable live shots unfolding on our
tv screens
the first plane crashed into the north
tower at 8 46 am
the second into the south tower at 903
am and then
within two hours both towers had
collapsed in a matter of seconds
virtually in free fall
i remember i struggled to make my way
down to lower manhattan that day
it was eerily quiet but for the
deafening sound of sirens
people were walking uptown in droves
stunned in silence
new york had become a city under siege
bridges and tunnels were closed
the phone systems were already stretched
beyond capacity and soon crashed
the grief the shock the chaos of that
day quickly gave way to anger
and calls for retribution
president george w bush had started his
presidency seven months earlier
in the evening of september 11 2001 he
addressed the nation and vowed to bring
to justice those responsible for what he
called these evil acts the u.s he said
would make no distinction between the
terrorists who committed these acts and
those who harbor them
soon comparisons were made with japan's
massive surprise attack on pearl harbor
during world war ii but of course this
was completely different
the air force of another power had not
attacked the united states these were
acts of terrorism evil as they were this
was not war
in the afternoon of that day we had
already been told that 19 men had
hijacked four planes and osama bin
laden's al-qaeda organization
was named as the culprit
bin laden had become america's enemy
number one in fact he had been since the
bombings of the u.s embassies in kenya
and tanzania a few years earlier
the speed with which the u.s government
named the perpetrators surprised many
and begged the question if u.s
intelligence was that good
why wasn't it able to thwart these
attacks
richard clark the top u.s official in
charge of counterterrorism at the time
made some damning claims following the
release of the much anticipated report
by the bipartisan congressional 911
commission whose mandate was to examine
and report on the facts and causes
relating to the attacks on september 11
he said quote
everybody involved in counterterrorism
in the cia
knew about it from the director on down
there were over 50 people who knew about
it 50 and they knew about it for over a
year and never once never once during
that year did they tell me or the
director of the fbi or the assistant
director of the fbi in charge of
counterterrorism
all of those 50 people kept it quiet
never told us for over a year
there was an
intentional policy approved at a high
level in cia to deny the information to
me and to the fbi
so were the 911 attacks a massive
intelligence and security failure or is
there more to it and did the united
states ultimately overreact by invading
afghanistan ousting the taliban from
power and being bogged down in a
two-decade war it did not win
i spoke earlier with ambassador paul
brenner who was chairman of the national
commission on terrorism in the lead up
to 9 11
and whose report titled countering the
changing threat of international
terrorism was delivered to then
president
bill clinton in 2000
it warned about al qaeda and other quote
loosely based terror groups
i began by asking him about the ominous
signs the growing chatter in the weeks
and days leading up to 9 11
about a possible even likely attack on
u.s soil and if
20 years later he thinks the u.s
government and intelligence agencies
failed
well yes of course they failed in the
sense that they didn't predict the
actual time and location of the attack
but as you pointed out the national
commission on terrorism
essentially said that the united states
took a vacation from history during the
1990s we congratulated ourselves on
defeating the soviet union
in 1989 and 1991
and we sort of thought we could ignore
what was going on around us but as the
national commission pointed out
beginning in the late 1980s and then all
through the 90s there was increasing
intelligence
of a growth of radical islamic
terrorism something we had not seen
before
and that's what the uh national
commission
tried to alert the country to uh
unfortunately of course we missed many
signals as it turned out but should
these signals have been missed because
as you say in your report
you mentioned that priority number one
is to prevent terrorist attacks saying
that good intelligence is the best
weapon against international
terrorism
could 911 have been prevented there was
plenty of intelligence
all around there was a lot of
intelligence that in retrospect we
should have picked up on the other hand
i've spent most of my adult life reading
intelligence and i know how difficult it
is to connect the dots in this case we
missed some dots particularly the fact
that
a couple of these terrorists as it
turned out were learning how to fly
planes how to take them off but not how
to land them which
obviously
uh meant that they were simply going to
crash them somewhere but can you just
say we missed some dots and simply move
on because the u.s had constant
intelligence on bin laden for at least a
full year before 9 11. we know that from
top u.s officials the us was flying
predator drones
for surveillance purposes over
afghanistan tracking bin laden's every
move in real time
president clinton famously said a few
years later quote i nearly got him and
could have killed him but i would have
had to destroy a little town called
kandahar and killed 300 innocent people
why were so many obvious signs missed
and so many dots simply not connected
well i think the problem is true of most
countries intelligence services they
are focused but they are very broadly
focused and in our case there were
misses between various intelligence
agencies for example between the
domestic intelligence from the fbi
and the international intelligence from
our national security
services this is not
unknown it is a tragedy there's no
question about it and it has obviously
changed
the world uh in a way that we had not
foreseen until
9 11.
but should there have been
consequences for these signs being
missed because
there was the president's daily brief
the intelligence report that was
handed over to president bush by the cia
on august 6 2001 entitled as you know
bin laden determined to strike in
the u.s there was also the comments that
were made by the fbi counterterrorism
chief john o'neill
who who said
that
the united states the s
the cia knew that two of the suspected
hijackers had received proper visas had
entered the united states
uh richard clard goes even further he
was leading counter-terrorism efforts
back then he accused the cia top brass
of intentionally denying information to
him and to the fbi
so so was the cia aware
of what was going on
the problem with picking over the
evidence afterwards always is that you
can find a document that says x
that people ignored what we had to do i
think what the american government had
to do i was not in the government what
the government had to do was react and
there i think president bush
reacted strongly with support
among other things from the cia
particularly in the initial phase of the
war in afghanistan
the initial phase of the war in
afghanistan i presume you agree with
those who say that
launching a war in response was not the
right thing to do it was not the most
cost effective not to mention not the
most efficient way to go after terrorism
no i i don't agree with that i think in
the circumstances of 3 000 americans
being killed the biggest attack on the
homeland since pearl harbor
the president whoever he had been it
could have been al gore or
george bush would have uh thought it was
a good idea to put some force on the
ground to try to get rid of the people
al-qaeda who had attacked us that i
think was clear and was widely supported
you said to put boots on the ground and
and go after the people who attacked you
you served in afghanistan and iraq with
hindsight do you accept that it was a
monumental blunder to invade these
countries it it's cost the us blood and
treasure and prestige and credibility
throughout the world not just trillions
of dollars spent on these post-9 11 wars
but the hundreds of thousands of deaths
maybe maybe millions the u.s now handed
afghanistan back to the taliban in
disgrace iraq isn't a mess it remains
unstable and al-qaeda let's face it is
not just around it's still alive and
well not just in the middle east but in
asia and africa isis was born from these
wars
well of course
the current situation which we can
discuss
is uh is not not good uh i would argue
that it would be worse if we had not
reacted if we had not in fact gone after
bin laden and finally got him
a decade later uh it would have been
worse if we had not gone into iraq
because iran would certainly have gotten
its nuclear weapons and probably iraq
would have gotten nuclear weapons also
hold on should bin laden have been
brought have been brought to justice
should the united states have captured
him
rather than rather than take him out and
execute him ten years later well as it
turned out we couldn't capture him the
the the force that went in to find him
in a lot of odd uh was attacked and they
had to respond with force and in the end
he was killed let me ask you this
ambassador
in 2000 your report recommended naming
afghanistan under the taliban as a state
sponsor of terrorism and applying all of
the sanctions
to to that country on 9 11
less than four hours i believe after the
attacks you said this
you said bin laden certainly has to be
the prime suspect but there are others
in the middle east and there are at
least two states iran and iraq which
should at least remain on the list of
potential suspects now of course that
was also the narrative
of the neoconservatives in washington
dick cheney donald rumsfeld paul
wolfowitz and so many others who
constantly tried to link
911 to these two countries to justify
military action against them
is it any coincidence that these same
people who are now in the white house
supported the so-called project for the
new american century which in open
letters to president clinton and
congressional leaders called for the
removal of saddam hussein
including
through the use of force if necessary
and in a report just before the 2000
election
that so-called new american century
project advocated that it would be
useful to provoke that shift
through a catastrophic event a
catalyzing event like a new pearl harbor
that event was 9 11 some would argue the
people advocating this were now in the
white house around bush they had their
moment their justification to invade
these foreign lands didn't they well
they certainly had a reason to you can
call it a justification i would uh they
certainly had a reason
uh particularly given the fact that we
know that uh al qaeda
uh conducted this attack and you know
this this was not something that was a
fantasy made up by neocons
if you go back and read the as you have
the report of the national commission on
terrorism we pointed out
that there had already been an attack on
the world trade center in 1993.
in which
the the men who we caught the fbi caught
said their intention had been to kill
200 000 americans by collapsing the two
buildings on each other
so the intelligence was there this was
it was not something that was made up by
neocons
that was paul bremer speaking with me
earlier you can watch more of that
interview on next week's insight america
as we discuss the legacy of the united
states wars in afghanistan and iraq
now in late 2002 the united states
government set up the national
commission on terrorist attacks upon the
united states also known as the 911
commission an independent bipartisan
body that was directed to prepare full
and complete account of the
circumstances surrounding the september
11th attacks including the preparedness
for and the immediate response
by u.s agencies on july 22 2004 the
commission released its report and among
its key findings were that communication
at senior levels was poor the chain of
command did not function well congress
responded slowly and gave little
guidance to executive branch agencies on
terrorism
the us has not been able to determine
the origin of the money used for the 9
11 attacks
according to the commission it also
found no evidence that the saudi
government as an institution
or senior saudi officials individually
funded al-qaeda the commission also made
41 recommendations including reforms of
u.s security and intelligence agencies
now for more on what we learned from the
911 commission and the questions that
remain unanswered to this day i'm joined
by one of its members richard benveniste
richard benveniste it's been now what 17
years since the commission issued those
findings
of course more has come to light in the
intervening years including fbi
investigation into some of the
the activities of the suspected
hijackers
does the report
that was authored in 2004 still stand
today if you knew back
then what you know you know today and
all the questions that do remain
unanswered would you sort of put your
name to it
oh yes uh i think the report stands up
very well frankly
i agree with much of your analysis
in the portion of the brenner interview
that i just saw
re-televised
i think your analysis is quite cogent
however if you look at the information
that has uh been revealed it is merely
supplemental to what we already found
anyone
doing investigations
that have a conclusion would be foolish
to suggest
that
there is no
further
information to be found that would be
arrogant and
incorrect
but in terms of the basic information
that we found yes
we had a lot of information
had it been utilized and shared and
uniformly distributed
to a central authority that would act
upon it
yes it is entirely possible that the
plot could have been interrupted
but do you believe that there were
gaping holes that the commission could
have looked into
as you know
families of the victims to this day are
angry
they believe they haven't been told the
complete truth do you believe that the
american public was given the full truth
about 9 11 given the fact that
there were several questions that were
unanswered just as an example
world trade center building number seven
collapsing that afternoon
the commission didn't look into it we
know that some media outlets including
the bbc reported on the collapse before
it even took place i mean these are
gaping holes aren't they do you feel
that more should have been done to get
to the heart of some of these key
questions
uh you are now plumbing into the uh
the realm of conspiratorialists
um there is no substantial evidence that
there was anything uh
other than
um the airplanes and the force of their
crashing into the buildings that was
result
in
building seven
there are no gaping holes
and
i'm sorry to tell you that you are
misinformed
if you think there are gaping holes what
there is is information that could yet
be pursued
we know that the
two individuals
who were in california were assisted by
individuals of saudi
connection
when they came to the united states but
as that's in our report as we said
uh
the uh level of assistance provided by
saudi individuals
was it was it was it investigated but
mr benveniste
for interrupting you but but let me just
ask you though
let me ask you though about uh
the accusations the accusations made
towards the commission that it did not
that it didn't give the whole story that
it did not relay all of the warning
signs that existed before 9 11. we know
from the chair and the co-chair of the
commission in a book that they
wrote a few years later that the
commission was in their words
set up to fail that the pentagon
officials from the pentagon and senior
officials from the
aviation federation administration
did not
give forthright answers to the extent
that they even considered a separate
investigation into obstruction of
justice
so today would you say you are
satisfied with everything that you put
out
you are getting information that we have
provided we provided the information
about the lapses in intelligence it's
all in our report we provided the
information that you've just referred to
about the
uh
failure to
track the planes and the mis statements
that were made
we made all of that available to the
public in open hearings we were
transparent
and we were as complete as we could be
there was no motive
on the
individuals who served on the commission
to do anything other than
provide a full
and uh realistic
appraisal of the facts and from those
facts make recommendations
to congress to make us safer as a
country and we did that
now what you are referring to
mr ben i am running out of time but just
a quick yes or no if i if if you may uh
do you agree with the comments that were
made by tom keane just a few days ago he
was the chairman of the 911 commission
he said
if the fbi and the ca and other 14
intelligence agencies had been talking
to each other most of us feel that the
attack would have been prevented do you
agree with him yesterday
i just said that i was just with him
yesterday i just met with the
victims families and we had a uh a
discussion for well over an hour that
was publicized televised um
you are
you are creating dissension where there
is no dissension
we are in violent agreement
that there was information which if it
had been shared
could have
resulted in the disruption of the 9 11
attacks unfortunately that didn't happen
and
the question of whether we over reacted
as a country the invasion of iraq was
somehow tied to 9 11 is one which we
have studied we have looked at and you
have made some legitimate points in that
regard but don't say that there were
gaping holes in the commission's report
because you are misinformed if you
believe that
well that's what many people would say
but for now though thank you so much
richard benveniste member of the 911
commission really good to have you on
the program thank you for your time
now in the aftermath of 9 11 several
major changes to surveillance laws in
the u.s
were enacted in the name of national
security the first change came with the
usa patriot act which was passed by
congress just 45 days
after the 9 11 attacks the new law
allowed u.s law enforcement officials to
monitor the phone and email
communications bank and credit records
as well as online activity of americans
it also expanded the list of activities
that qualify for terrorism charges and
authorized the indefinite detention
without trial of immigrants and non-us
citizens
now several legal challenges have been
brought against the patriot act because
of government overreach and abuse and
federal courts have ruled that a number
of its provisions are unconstitutional
now after parts of the patriot act
expired back in june of 2015
and following much outcry from the
public and civil rights groups here in
the u.s the usa freedom act was enacted
into law it placed limits on the
collection of communication data on u.s
citizens but also re-enacted some of the
patriot acts expired sections through to
2019. now for more on the impact of
these post-9 11 laws on freedoms and
civil liberties here in the united
states i'm joined by imran siddiqui the
executive director in washington state
of care the council on american islamic
relations
imran siddiqui in the immediate
aftermath of 9 11 of course the american
muslim community not just in new york
but across
the united states were subjected to
greater surveillance and racial
profiling through the patriot act there
was also the backlash that they faced as
muslims living in this country the the
suspicions
that surrounded them
and which were reinforced by these new
laws there's the demonization the anger
the rise in death threats the hate
crimes how challenging was it for muslim
americans in those days
it was definitely challenging uh just in
the aftermath of of this horrific attack
we're all mourning as a country i had
friends and family members who were
impacted who were in new york city at
the time so
we as a community really didn't even get
a chance to mourn what was happening
because this level of suspicion really
was turned on to us uh immediately and
you found yourself
um you know having to defend yourself
for things that you were not responsible
for and so
uh slowly you started seeing this push
for you know different wars and things
of that nature you start seeing
um this push for mass surveillance that
took place on both a
local state and federal level and that
impacted our communities nationwide
additionally you started seeing um
informants being placed in in mosques
across the united states and so this
level of of distrust and criminalization
was fomented within our community so it
was definitely challenging
the government said that many of these
laws actually helped them
to disrupt
potential terrorist plots to strengthen
security to what extent did it undermine
the civil liberties especially of
the muslim community and i remember
when i lived in new york during the
period in the lead up and in the
aftermath of 9 11 it wasn't just muslims
who were living fearfully but it was
also people who who could be
misrepresented taken for muslims i
remember cab drivers staying away from
their work uh not just uh
cab drivers who were muslim but even
those who were hindu
that their turbans were mistaken for for
the
the gear that
that muslims might wear to what extent
was there
unwarranted suspicion and how did it
impact the way muslims lived not just
back then but how they relate today to
to america and their role within within
american society that's a great point um
the first person who was who was killed
in the aftermath of 9 11 in a
retribution attack was a sikh american
in mesa arizona named belbir singh sodhi
and this was a sikh american who wore a
turban
just because of
the
perception that this person is foreign
or uh because terrorists wear turbans or
have beards
the sikh american community was very
much the victim of a
massive uptick in hate crimes and you
see this taking place to this very day
and so
islamophobia not only impacted muslim
americans it impacted folks who were
perceived as being muslim as well and to
the point of
mass surveillance and these types of
programs what you see in places like new
york city where you lived where they had
a
demographics unit where they uh they
basically
spied on 33 ancestries of interest all
of which were of muslim descent where
they placed spies in
cafes and mosques and around the city
and not even around the city but
throughout the entire northeast
following
student conferences
and and muslim conferences throughout
throughout the region
no actionable intelligence was actually
gathered through these spying programs
and so around the 2011 time frame new
york city had to
dismantle the spying program after
backlash by organizers and the muslim
community locally within within new york
city so
this type of mass surveillance has never
proven to
actually stop terrorism um i think this
was an overreaction by both city state
and federal uh levels and it was
deployed across different cities
throughout the us and it it has a
chilling effect amongst muslims because
we were otherwise this is a repeat of
the type of tactics that were used
during the 1960s and 70s during the
cointelpro era against black american
organizations and other organizations
where you're treated as criminals first
and then citizens second
all right and interesting that in 2000
the fbi registered 28 incidents of hate
crimes against american muslims in 2001
after the attacks
that number went up to 481 imran
siddiqui thank you so much for joining
us
now less than a month after the
september 11th attacks on october 7th of
the first day of the war in afghanistan
the u.s used a drone for the first time
to conduct a lethal strike in combat it
killed two unidentified men this was
just the beginning of a new paradigm of
warfare remote killings by drones by the
united states and others with no
accountability with complete impunity
this new weapon of choice meant no risk
of u.s casualties and an ability to to
perpetrate acts of war
largely hidden from the american public
also hidden over the past two decades
where the tens of thousands of civilian
casualties killed in far away countries
that are not at war with the united
states
now according to the uk-based non-profit
air wars since 9 11
over 48 000 civilians are estimated to
have been directly killed by u.s
airstrikes in seven conflict zones
in countries including afghanistan
pakistan yemen and somalia
the u.s has declared over 91 000 drone
strikes since 9 11 a report from the
costs of war project estimates that post
9 11 wars and counterterrorism
operations have killed more than 900 000
people
but of course the true figure
of the number of civilians
killed
may never be fully known now the lack of
transparency around this form of
extraditional killing has undermined of
course the moral standing of the united
states which has been accused by
human rights organizations violating
international norms and law philip
alston exports the legal justification
of killings quote far from the battle
zone during his time as united nations
special rapporteur on extrajudicial
summary or arbitrary executions he is
now director of new york university
school of laws center for human rights
and global justice
he joins us now live now philip alston i
know that in your report back in 2010
you were already highly critical of u.s
drone attacks saying that its growing
use was undermining global constraints
on the use of military force at the time
i know you estimated that around 40
states
already had drone technology
today it's about 100 states
how do you contain their use how do you
uphold international law
well drones of course
are now an established part of the
military arsenal as well as civilian
arsenal of
of a huge number of states
um i'm not sure where your figure of a
hundred comes from but uh i suspect they
are
even more widely used
the challenge of course is to
restrict the
ways and the extent to which they are
used to carry out killings
that's what makes the
difference between
drones that are used simply for
surveillance and those that are used to
carry out lethal attacks
there
are in place but they were in place
before 2001.
[Music]
international legal rules
that limit the circumstances under which
those sorts of targeted lethal killings
can take place
but the united states has managed to
either ignore
or to try to create legal justifications
to get around those restrictions
but outside outside of declared
wars
in countries like somalia like yemen
like pakistan other countries that are
not at war with the united states does
the use of drones to kill quote-unquote
suspects
amount to extrajudicial killings
in my view they
in principle do obviously one has to
look at the circumstances of any
particular
use
but it is legitimate to use um
drones to carry out killings in the
context of areas of active hostilities
in other words where there's an armed
conflict going on
but what the united nati united states
has done
is to extend that notion talking about a
global war on terror
talking about uh hostilities that are
linked to the original
conflict in afghanistan or iraq or syria
and thus carry out killings in a range
of other countries and in my view
virtually all of those killings violate
the appropriate international legal
framework
and of course the united states as you
know and as you've pointed out argues
that it's post 9 11 laws enables it to
legally use these drones to to to kill
those it suspects of being terrorists
but but when we talk about international
law
uh because any any country could
otherwise just you know
enact a set of laws overnight to justify
these killings when you look at
international law
can you imagine what might happen if any
country from the south and you know
choose your pick would kill buy drones
suspects in
countries like the us france or
australia or any other country wouldn't
it be deemed immediately illegal
wouldn't the united nations security
council take immediate
measure the question is isn't there a
clear double standard and what kind of
of paramed parameters should the united
nations set
for the use of these drones
i don't think there's a double standard
on the part of the united nations i
think the un has spoken out pretty
clearly
and condemned the ways in which the
united states has conducted these
killings i first challenged the united
states back in 2004
in response to a killing that had taken
place earlier in yemen
where there was no armed conflict going
on
and that was quite a prolonged and
extended
discussion with the united states which
led me to conclude that the killing was
not possibly justified under
international law
but your point about the double standard
more in political terms is absolutely
right
if you were to
go to
china today
and the chinese were to say
we believe following us precedents
that we have a right to
[Music]
conduct lethal drone strikes against
individuals who we believe are a threat
to china's security
and some of those individuals seem to
reside in the united states or in my own
country australia
there would of course be absolute
outrage
but that's the message that i and others
were trying to send to the united states
long ago to say look
you can make up these rules to suit
yourself
but
sooner or later you'll be setting
precedence
and those precedents are absolutely
unacceptable that in turn means that
your own behavior is not acceptable
and so i think the double standard is
very powerful and very strong but it's
on the part of the united states and not
on the part of the united nations
but of course i mean the question
remains philip alston but we are running
out of time the question remains how you
uphold the rule of law if so-called
suspected terrorists and the term is
often lose used quite loosely at world
with no
proof
presented we saw it again in kabul not
long ago the whole family
wiped out when they're killed in these
drone strikes and not brought to justice
how do you end this impunity uh for the
killings one might see even
assassinations of
of so many civilians um we'll have to
leave it for now though philip alston
always great to have you thank you very
much
now detainees wearing orange jumpsuits
surrounded by razor wire and guard posts
the detention center at guantanamo bay
the u.s naval base on cuban soil became
a symbol of injustice during the
so-called war on terror
created as a place to interrogate and
hold individuals the u.s didn't want to
bring to trial before u.s courts
now over time reports of brutal
treatment and indefinite detention were
revealed and guantanamo became a source
of international outrage and
condemnation
today the facility is still in operation
since the george w bush administration
established gitmo in 2002 780 men have
been detained in cells on the island
although president obama signed an
executive order in 2009 to close the
detention camp and president biden has
supported its closure
39 detainees remain
most of them 17 are being held without
charges and are not recommended for
transfer to another country another 10
are being held in detention but are
recommended for transfer if security
conditions are met
10 face charges for war crimes but only
two
of those 39 detainees have been
convicted of a war crime
i'm now joined by mansoor adafi he is a
former detainee at guantanamo who was
held for over 14 years
without charge
mansur adaifi
when you look back
at your time in guantanamo how do you
look back on the 14 years that you spent
largely in
isolation
in solitary confinement in communicado
and the fact that you were never
charged with any crime
uh
uh first of all as you said that
guantanamo is a simple now of injustice
torture abuse of power lawlessness and
uh
indefinite detention also a death
sentence for the people who still there
when i look back
at
my life at guantanamo we
we spent years and years tried to figure
out even until i left
why i was there
i never achieved the
charge with the crime we couldn't
understand why why they brought us to
that place so
guantanamo uh changed
every time that the first time it was
said to be interrogation and gather uh
again actionable intelligence that would
save america and american lives
but then when general jeep lee uh
jeffrey miller arrived in 2000 by the
end of
the guantanamo detention uh changed to
be
experimenting lab what they call it
america's battle lab
do you know jeffrey miller is the first
one who started uh developing enhanced
interrogation technique or enhanced
torture
technique
and interestingly i know that um
well you were captured when you were
just 18 and you've also recounted
recounted in your memoir don't forget us
here how you came of age
in guantanamo
you wrote
that's the thing about the americans
they believed anything but the truth how
did your experience
there shape your view of america and
when you call on the u.s administration
i know you you wrote an open letter to
president biden with five or six other
former detainees asking him to close
down the facility
asking the us government to apologize
to acknowledge what happened and to
compensate the victims how likely is any
of this to happen realistically
of course like as you know i was sold to
the cia at the age of 18 shipped to
guantanamo at the age of 19.
some some people ask me how do you live
your twenties i had i
i answered i don't know what i don't
know what what twenties me in my life
because i spent all almost have my life
behind the uh at guantanamo
so uh
we were told we wrote a letter to
president biden to close the detention
because it is as as you all know uh
people have been held for the last 20
years with our charge without
any kind of
any right because guantanamo is outside
the law and
the message
the united states government tried to
send to the world that they cannot cross
any line they they won't abide by any
laws this the purpose of guantanamo is
going to know about it's not about
safety or
security
so for me 15 around 15 years at
guantanamo it's like a huge gap in my uh
life and
and we hope that biden can close the uh
play uh place one uh once for all
mansur adaifi thank you very much
for sharing
this painful story with us i know that
other guantanamo detainees like
mazenberg have spoken about the
dehumanization
they were subjected to saying they
learned how to stop thinking of
themselves as humans as as husbands and
fathers but
rather as numbers the detainee numbers
they were given at guantanamo
now for years the u.s used torture
against detainees at guantanamo and
other u.s detention facilities around
the world
john kiriyaku a former cia analyst and
case officer who was involved in
counter-terrorism missions with the
central intelligence agency
following 911
was the first former cia officer to blow
the whistle and confirm
in 2007 that the cia was using
waterboarding he joins me now and john
kiriakou you also revealed that this
practice this form of torture was not
carried out by just a few rogue
elements of heroic agents within the cia
but was official u.s policy that was
approved at the highest level of
government and for that you not not
those who carried out the orders or
signed off on that practice went to jail
the us government called it enhanced
interrogation techniques
how widespread how abusive were these
these measures quote unquote these
techniques to use the government's
euphemism
well these measures were supposed to be
very uh closely held and used only on a
very small number of detainees at least
that's what we were told inside the cia
but the truth was that they were
actually very widely used used not
only by the cia but also by the us
military and so where inside the cia we
were led to believe that it was only
four or five maybe six detainees who
were being subject to these torture
techniques it was actually many dozens
of people
and of course the government officials
at the time
during the bush administration and
republican lawmakers claimed repeatedly
that torture worked and that it actually
led to actionable intelligence the cia
said that as well for years however
immoral illegal it might have been
did they work
absolutely not
absolutely not there is ample proof
ample evidence it's been well documented
in a number of different places that
these torture techniques never worked a
victim of torture will tell you anything
that he thinks you want to hear just to
get you to stop torturing him he'll make
up names addresses
events just to get you to stop and then
you have to commit a team of analysts to
vet the information by the time that
happens by the time that's completed
even if there was an attack plan the
attack probably has taken place
otherwise you've wasted
hundreds perhaps thousands of man hours
trying to vet unreliable information it
never works
yeah back in 2002 you led the cia team
that captured al-qaeda member abu
zubaydah in pakistan
when you consider that bin laden was not
captured alive and brought to justice
that he was eventually found and killed
in pakistan in 2011
and when president obama famously said
that justice was then served was it
really obama
bin laden was not just someone that the
cia had recruited many years before to
fight the soviets but he was also
possibly just a symbol wasn't he when
really the real strategist the chief
ideologue of al-qaeda might have been
someone else might have been al-zawahiri
it's hard to believe that he couldn't
have been captured alive why wasn't he
i don't think they ever intended to
capture bin laden alive i think that uh
that they had made a policy
determination that osama bin laden would
never really talk if he were to be
captured that even if he did talk the
information that he would have provided
wouldn't have been anything that we
didn't already know from other detainees
and i think that that the feeling of of
the necessity of vengeance was so strong
inside the u.s government and especially
at the white house and the cia that the
plan from the very beginning was to kill
him if we had the opportunity to kill
him remember we had already captured abu
zubaydah we had already captured
mohammed
abdul rahima nashori ramsey beneship we
had a lot of high
al-qaeda detainees that we already had
who were already talking they had been
debriefed by the or interrogated by the
fbi
they didn't really need bin laden's
information but they certainly wanted
him dead
it wouldn't have been wouldn't it have
been crucial to to capture him and to
have him a stand trial essentially to
present the evidence that
still might be missing to to this day at
the end of the day bin laden
it's interesting and surprising i guess
at the same time wasn't wanted by the
fbi for 911 specifically but rather he
was wanted in connection with the 1998
bombings of the two u.s embassies in
india
and nairobi
would it have been far better when you
look back
at the way the united states and the cia
prosecuted this war on terror to have
captured someone like him and what has
happened to azawahiri and the other
leaders of this movement
i think that's one of the most important
questions that that somebody can ask and
the answer is a resounding yes if the
united states is serious about
projecting
an image to the rest of the world of
being a country run by the rule of law
and by justice then the only alternative
is to capture him and to put him on
trial and and that way we can show the
rest of the world that we're serious
about justice we're serious about
winning justice for those 3 000 victims
of 9 11.
but
the policy was so short-sighted that
vengeance was chosen over justice but
you're absolutely right it's it's always
better to capture than to kill because
there's a there's a chance that somebody
will talk and give you actionable
intelligence
and then you can prosecute them and show
the world that you're serious about your
own system uh that just never happened
our john cariacco former cia agent and
whistleblower thank you very much really
appreciate having you on the program
and and speaking of short-sightedness
the problem with the us approach is
perhaps that it purports to target
terrorists not
terrorism it doesn't address
the phenomenon of terrorism which is not
new
nor does it address its underlying
causes
today there is no compulsion to bomb
people with complete
impunity because these people happen to
be
living in faraway lands they happen to
brown people they happen to be muslims
now what can be concluded 20 years after
the fateful events of 9 11
that shocked the world and humanity
the immediate effect of that day was
instantaneous
the united states
were united the entire world friends and
foes alike also
united with america
but that brief moment of unison of
humanity
was squandered when america invaded and
occupied afghanistan
in vengeance and then iraq and
prosecuted with its allies its
never-ending war on terror
and even though
biden has pulled us troops out of
afghanistan these hidden wars will
continue
a war that benefited few and alienated
many
wars the destroyed
nations wars that tarnished the moral
standing of the united
remember states torture black sites
targeted killings and the list
goes on
the us may not have lost a single battle
that's true but it lost the war and its
standing with it even among its own
allies and 20 years on hundreds of
thousands of deaths and trillions of
dollars later
the war it unleashed on a rag-tag
elusive enemy it helped create in the
first place
continues america
and american democracy is slowly coming
to the conclusion that the greater enemy
may not be the enemy without but
the enemy
within
it's hard to believe that it's been 20
years since that fateful day september
11 2001.
and that is all for this special edition
of inside america with mirita here in
washington for me and the entire team
thanks for watching
[Music]
you